(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-08-07T10:27:21.446455",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ここは1人の女の子が夢を追いかけた場所
This is the place where a single girl chased her dreams.
ここは1人の女の子が夢を掴んだ場所
This is the place where a single girl caught her dream.
私、湊あくあは
I, Minato Aqua,
2024年8月28日をもって
will graduate on August 28, 2024...
ホロライブを卒業します。
I'll graduate from Hololive.
みなさんどうもあくあです！
Hello everyone, I'm Aqua!
5周年記念で3Dライブがあって
With the 5th Anniversary and 3D Live happening...
そしてみんながいてくれて
and everyone being there for me,
私がいて...
and me being there too...
できた！
We made it!
みなさまのおかげで、え、無事
Thanks to everyone, I've safely...
6周年を迎えることができました！
reached my 6th anniversary!
湊あくあ ～卒業～
Minato Aqua ~Graduation~
等身大のインタビュー
[Title: Unfiltered Interview]
本日はインタビューよろしくお願いします。
Thank you for the interview today.
よろしくお願いします！
Yes, thank you!
ではまずお名前を教えてください。
First, please tell me your name.
はい、えっと湊あくあです。
Yes... I'm Minato Aqua.
湊ってどういう漢字書かれるんですか？
What is the meaning behind "Minato"?
えっと、(さんずい)に奏でるで湊です。
It's "Minato" with a water radical and "play music."
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
ではご職業は何をされていますか？
Now, what is your occupation?
アイドルです。
I'm an idol.
アイドルです！
I'm an idol!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
では続いて、好きな食べ物はなんですか？
Next, what is your favorite food?
ずっとオムライスだったんですけど
It had always been omurice, but...
最近変わりまして
recently that changed.
卵です！
It's eggs!
素材が好きでした最近気づきました。
I realized I liked the base ingredient.
はい！好きです！
Yes, I love them!
塩胡椒かな...あ、同じですね。ありがとうございます。
Salt and pepper, I guess? Same here, thank you!
ずばり湊とあくあさんのチャームポイントは？
What is Minato Aqua's charm point?
後頭部です。
My back of the head.
これ以上は言えません。
I can't say anything beyond this.
あ、何か触れてはいけないんでしょうかね。
Is it something we shouldn't touch?
はいちょっと色々あってあ、すみません。
Yes, various things... I'm sorry.
好きな色はあくあ色です。
My favorite color is Aqua color!
ピンクと水色であくあ色良いです！
Pink and light blue make Aqua color, and it's great!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
ホロライブプロダクションに所属して、湊あくあさん自身が成長したなって思うところはありますか？
Is there anything about joining Hololive Production where you felt you grew?
成長...でもやっぱり、えっと、人と円滑にコミュニケーションが取れるようになりました。
Well, I became able to communicate smoothly with people.
これまでの活動してきた中で1番の思い出はなんですか？
What is your fondest memory from your activities so far?
色々あるんですけど、やっぱり1番と言ったらソロライブと全体ライブです。
There are many, but if I had to pick the top ones, it's my solo live and the group concert.
ソロライブをすることはデビューした当時からの目標で
Doing a solo live was a goal since my debut.
ステージに立った時はすごく緊張したけどみんなの応援のおかげで頑張れました。
Standing on stage was very nerve-wracking, but thanks to everyone's support, I did my best.
みんなが照らしてくれたあくあ色のサイリウムの景色は今でも忘れません。
I will never forget the view of the Aqua-colored penlights everyone shone for me.
それでは続きまして、今1番腹を割ってお話ししたい人はいますか？
Is there anyone you most want to talk to now that you've made it through?
あぁ...YAGOO社長
YAGOO.
お久しぶりです。
It's been a while.
覚えてますか？
Do you remember me?
もちろんです。
Of course I do.
本当ですか？
Really?
あ、あの...緊張されてますか？
Are you nervous?
いや、大丈夫です。
No, I'm okay.
私はめちゃくちゃ緊張しています。
I am extremely nervous.
あの、今日は...お時間をいただきありがとうございます。
Thank you for taking the time today.
こちらこそありがとうございます。
Thank you as well.
ずっとたくさん聞きたいことがいっぱいあるので、ちょっと今日は...お話ししていければと思います。
I have a lot of things I want to ask, so I hope we can just talk today.
はい、いっぱい喋ってくださいね。
Yes, please talk a lot!
ちょっと...苦手なんで喋るの、お願いします！
I'm not very good at talking, but please!
じゃあ 1個目からいきます。
Now then, let's start with the first one.
はい。
Yes.
え、まず、えっと、簡単なものから
Um, first of all, starting with something simple...
え、責任感で、社長としての責任感で 胃が痛くなったりとか、うわぁってなったりすることはありますか?
Um, out of a sense of responsibility as CEO, have you ever had your stomach hurt or felt like "Oh no"?
あんまり？あんまり緊張するタイプではないかなという風に思いますかね。
Not really? I don't really get nervous, I suppose.
本当ですか？
Really?
はい。ただまあ、基本日々、いろいろ課題を抱えているので、
Yes. But basically every day, I'm dealing with various challenges,
“これを今日やらなきゃ”って感じで朝早く起きちゃうことはありますね。
so I sometimes wake up early thinking, "I have to do this today."
あ、じゃあちょっと、なんかホロライブについて聞こうと思います。
Ah, then let's talk a bit about Hololive.
はい。え、まずは、どうしてホロライブを作ろうと思ったんですか？
Yes. First of all, why did you decide to create Hololive?
そうですね、なんというか、元々その初音ミクさんみたいな、あいうキャラクターで、海外の人も含めてその楽しませような、そういうコンテンツっていいなと思っていましたと。
Well, how should I put it? Originally, I thought it would be great to have content like Hatsune Miku, featuring characters that could entertain people overseas as well.
でも、まあ初音ミクさんって初音ミクさん以外の人がいるわけではないので、たくさんの人が人気になれるわけではないなっていうふうに思っている中で、
However, since Hatsune Miku is just Hatsune Miku and there aren't others, not everyone can become popular.
なんかVTuber的なシステムっていうのを自分たちで開発して、そういう、いろんな配信者さんだったりとか、そういうクリエーターの方が
So, thinking about that, we developed a VTuber-like system ourselves so that various streamers and creators
初音ミクさんのような、バーチャルタレントとして活動できるとすごく、あの、世界中のファンの方を喜ばせることができるかもしれないと思って、
could act as virtual talents like Hatsune Miku, which might make fans all over the world happy.
あの、ホロライブのシステムを開発して、こういう、あのサービスを始めようと思いました。
So we developed the Hololive system and decided to start this service.
ああ、え、じゃあその、まさかこんな大所帯になるとは思っていなかったって感じなんですかね、最初は。
Ah, so you didn't expect it to become such a massive group at first, right?
最初はそうですね、あの、こんなに大所帯になるとは、まあ、ある程度やっぱり海外の方に、あの、すごくたくさんの方のファンの方に届けていきたいと思っていたので、
At first, well... we did want to reach a lot of fans overseas to some extent,
もちろんその、規模として大きいものを目指してましたけれど、あの、まあ予想よりも、あの、順調に成長しているのかなとは思います。
so of course we aimed for something large in scale, but I think it has grown even smoother than expected.
おお、なんか、ちゃんと社長ですね？ちゃんとし、これ失礼なのかな？ちゃんと社長ですね！すごい！
Oh! You're really acting like a CEO, aren't you? Is it rude to say that? You're properly a CEO! Amazing!
じゃあ続いて、ここまでホロライブのお話を聞かせていただいたんですけど、次は
Now moving on, we've talked about Hololive so far, but next...
私、湊あくあについて聞いていこうと思います。ちょっとここが一番大事です！よろしくお願いします！
I'd like to ask about me, Minato Aqua. This part is the most important! Please!
それでは行きます。
Let's go.
え、私、湊あくあは、ホロライブプロダクションに貢献できていましたか？ズバリ！教えてください！
Um, did I, Minato Aqua, contribute to Hololive Production? Tell me directly!
貢献できていたと思いますね。
I think you definitely contributed.
まあ、あの、ホロライブプロダクションというよりもやっぱり湊あくあさんっていうタレントさんがやっぱり、まあ、TikTokとかでも流行るような楽曲みたいなものを提供、提供というか、あの、まあ、なんていうかそういった活動を実現することができて、
Well, rather than Hololive Production as a whole, Minato Aqua as a talent provided songs that would trend on TikTok and similar platforms, making such activities possible,
まあ、いろんなその、若い人にとっての、なんか憧れの存在とかになれたんじゃないかなっていうふうには思っています。
and I think she became an existence of admiration for many young people.
そう思いますか？え、ちょっとどんな印象を持たれているんですか？湊あくあに対して。
You think so? What kind of impression do you have of Minato Aqua?
まあ、基本的にはすごく芯の強い方だなというふうには思っています。
Well, basically, I think she has a very strong core.
はい。ただ、ま活動としてはやっぱり、
Yes. But as for her activities,
なんだろうね、そのアイドル的な側面もあると思うんですけど、やっぱり配信の、まあ、なんだろう、ゲームがうまいっていうところがやっぱり、あの、もっとも、はい、こう、なんていうか、ギャップ的、ギャップっていうとあれですけどね。はい。になる部分なのかなと思いました。
while she has an idol-like aspect, the fact that she's really good at streaming and games is probably what creates the biggest gap.
わかりました。はい。それでは最後に、ちょっとここまでの質問ばかりだったんだけれども
I see. Yes. Now finally, up until now it's been mostly my questions,
社長から、え、私への、なんか伝えたいことなどあったりしますでしょうか？
but is there anything you, the CEO, would like to convey to me?
そうですね、やっぱり、6年という長い期間、あの、活動していただいて本当にありがとうございましたというところと、本当にお疲れ様でしたという。
Well, first of all, thank you very much for being active for such a long period of 6 years, and truly, thank you for your hard work.
あ、ありがとうございます！っていう形ですね。はい。僕としてもまだまだ心残りの部分もあるんだけれど、
Ah, thank you! That's how it is. Yes. As for me, I still have some lingering regrets, but
本当にこの6年ご一緒できたことがすごく良かったと思っております。
I am truly glad we were able to spend these 6 years together.
ありがとうございます本当にホロライブに入れていただいてありがとうございました！
Thank you so much! Thank you for letting me join Hololive!
ということで、なんかちょっとエモい感じになりましたけれども、こんな感じで、対談は以上ということで。
So, it got a bit emotional, but with that, our dialogue concludes here.
ありがとうございました
Thank you very much.
お疲れ様でした
Thank you for your hard work.
社長と話してみていかがでしたか？
How was it talking with the president?
めちゃ緊張しました
I was super nervous.
なんか、生きてるんだなって実感しました
It made me realize... that he's actually alive.
そうですね、生きてらっしゃいますね
That's right, he is indeed alive.
あまりこれまで活動してきて社長と話することってなかったですか？あくあさん
Haven't you had much chance to talk with the president throughout your activities, Aqua-san?
やっぱり、まあそうですね社長だし、YAGOOはなんか妖精みたいな存在だから、なんか一生会えない天然記念物なのかなぐらいに思ってました
Well, since he's the president, and YAGOO is like a fairy, I honestly thought he was like a natural monument I'd never get to meet.
あ、そうなんですね
Oh, is that so?
ちゃんといました。ちゃんと存在してましたか、よかったです
He was really there. He actually existed, so that's good.
では続いての質問です。今一番感謝を伝えたい人はいますか？
Now for the next question. Is there someone you'd like to express your gratitude to the most right now?
いっぱいいますけど、一番はマネージャーさんです
There are a lot of people, but most of all, my manager.
あ、マネージャーさん
Oh, your manager.
手紙を書いてきたので読みます
I wrote a letter, so I'll read it.
ありがとうございます。では手紙よろしくお願いします
Thank you very much. Go ahead with the letter, please.
マネージャーさんへ
To my manager,
マネージャーさん！お元気ですか？
Manager! How are you doing?
マネージャーさんのことは配信でもちょくちょく話が出てくる、えーユニコーンのアイコンだった、有能マネージャーさんです。
You're the capable manager with the unicorn icon, whom I frequently talk about on stream.
2020年頃から約4年間お世話になりました。
Thank you for looking after me for about 4 years since around 2020.
ホロライブでは担当マネージャーさんが変わることがよくある中で、ここまで変わることなく来れたこと、ものすごく奇跡だと思ってます。
In Hololive, it's common for assigned managers to change, so being able to keep the same one all this time feels like a complete miracle.
担当した当時の私は、まだめちゃガキで尖っていてマネージャーさんに何度もご迷惑をおかけしたと思います。
When you first took charge of me, I was still super immature and edgy, and I'm sure I caused you trouble countless times.
今でも、私が配信ばかりして返事かえすの遅かったり、時々通じない日本語を使ってしまったりしてご迷惑をおかけしました。
Even now, I'd cause trouble by being too busy streaming to reply promptly, or sometimes using Japanese that didn't make sense.
それでも、ここまで見捨てず担当して下さりありがとうございました。
Even so, thank you for not giving up on me and continuing to manage me.
いつも現場に行くとジュースとお菓子を用意してくださったり、旅行のお土産をくれました。
Whenever I went to the studio, you'd prepare juice and snacks, or bring me souvenirs from trips.
外の仕事が苦手でいつもご飯を食べこなくても仕事が頑張れたのはマネージャーさんのおかげです。
Since I'm bad at working outside and wouldn't always eat properly, being able to push through was thanks to you.
私が人間関係や社会との向き合い方で悩んでいた時も、たくさんアドバイスや元気づけてくださる言葉をくれました。
Whenever I struggled with human relationships or how to face society, you gave me lots of advice and encouraging words.
田舎から上京して何も分からなくて、親元を離れ頼る人もいなかった時も、第3の母として支えて下さりました。
When I moved to Tokyo from the countryside knowing nothing, away from my parents and with no one to rely on, you supported me like a third mother.
第1の母はあくみこ、
My first mother is Akumiko,
第2の母はマリン、
My second mother is Marine,
第3の母はマネージャーさんです。
And my third mother is my manager.
この4年間、たくさん愛情を込めて湊あくあをサポートして下さり本当にありがとうございました。
Thank you so much for putting so much love into supporting Minato Aqua over these 4 years.
私の担当でいてくれて本当に良かったです！
I'm so glad you were my manager!
湊あくあより
From Minato Aqua.
素敵ななお手紙ありがとうございます。マネージャーさん感動してましたね
Thank you for the wonderful letter. Your manager looked touched.
これ本当に感動してんのかな？
Is he really touched though?
あくあ自身もなんかすごい、なんか涙出そうな感じが、私が泣くわこれ！
I myself feel like... wait, tears are coming, I'm gonna cry!
あくあさんにとって第3のお母さんです、第2のマリンで引こん引こんだげど涙、違うねちょっと第2のマリンでちょっとくすって笑いになっちゃったんですけども、いや本当に感謝してます
To Aqua-san, she's the third mother—wait, I pulled back on the second mother Marine part with tears—no wait, I chuckled a bit about Marine, but truly, I'm so grateful.
それでは最後の質問です。あくあさんご自身において変わらないものは何ですか？
Now for the final question. What is something about yourself, Aqua-san, that never changes?
変わらないもの…
Something that never changes...
ここは一人の女の子が夢を追いかけた場所
This is the place where a girl chased her dreams.
ここは一人の女の子が夢をつかんだ場所
This is the place where a girl grasped her dreams.
そしてここは一人の女の子が新たな道を歩み出す場所
And this is the place where a girl sets out on a new path.
湊あくあさんにとってホロライブとは？
What does Hololive mean to Minato Aqua?
好きだった…この場所…
I loved... this place...
やめられない漫画を途中で閉じて
Closing an unputdownable manga halfway,
顔を上げて気づくように
As if looking up and realizing,
心地いい日向もいつの間にか
The pleasant sunlight before I knew it
影になって黄昏る
Turned into shadows at twilight.
君と会って過ぎる時間忘れるくらい夢中で話した
Meeting you, talking so intently I forgot the time passing,
僕の夢はここではないどこへ
My dream is heading somewhere that isn't here.
帰り道は 帰り道は 遠回りしたくなるよ
On the way home, on the way home, I want to take the long way around.
どこへ行けば どこに着くか?
Where should I go, where will I arrive?
過去の道なら迷うことがないから
If it's a path of the past, I won't get lost, so...
弱虫 (弱虫...) 新しい世界へ
Cowardly (Cowardly...) To a new world
今行きたい 行きたい 行きたい 行きたい 強くなりたい
Now I want to go, want to go, want to go, want to go, I want to be strong.
Oh! Oh! Oh! 好きだった…この場所…
Oh! Oh! Oh! I loved... this place...
Oh! Oh! Oh! 一歩目…踏み出そう!
Oh! Oh! Oh! Take... the first step!
街灯りが寂しくと 感じるのは
Feeling the streetlights lonely
見慣れた景色と違うから
Is because it's different from the familiar scenery.
いつもの高架線が見えなくなって
The usual overpass can't be seen,
どこにいるか分からない
And I don't know where I am.
人は誰も 変わることに慣れていなくて昨日と同じように今日も明日もここにいたくなるんだ
No one is used to changing, so like yesterday, today and tomorrow too, I want to stay here.
知らない道 知らない道 あと何回 歩けるだろう
Unknown paths, unknown paths, how many more times can I walk them?
夢の方へ 愛の方へ 風は道を選んだりはしないよ
Toward dreams, toward love, the wind doesn't choose its path.
このまま (このまま...) ONE WAYの標識でも行くいんだ 行くいんだ 行くいんだ 行くいんだ 戻れなくても…
Just like this (Just like this...) Even with a ONE WAY sign, I'm going, going, going, going...
君と離れるのは寂しいけど大事な別れだ
It's sad to part with you, but it's an important farewell.
もっともっと広い世界 知らなくちゃいけない
I must know a much, much wider world.
君と離れるのは悲しいけど大事な別れだ
It's sad to part with you, but it's an important farewell.
もともと広い世界 知らなきゃいけない
I have to know the vast world from the start.
いつかきっと違う道を休んだり
Someday, resting on a different path,
輝く未来のための
For a shining future,
帰り道は 帰り道は 遠回りしたくなるよ
On the way home, on the way home, I want to take the long way around.
どこへ行けば どこに着くか?
Where should I go, where will I arrive?
過去の道なら迷うことがないから
If it's a path of the past, I won't get lost, so...
弱虫 (弱虫...) 新しい世界へ
Cowardly (Cowardly...) To a new world
今行きたい 行きたい 行きたい 行きたい 強くなりたい
Now I want to go, want to go, want to go, want to go, I want to be strong.
Oh! Oh! Oh! 好きだった…この場所…
Oh! Oh! Oh! I loved... this place...
Oh! Oh! Oh! 一歩目…踏み出そう!
Oh! Oh! Oh! Take... the first step!
拝啓 人類は快晴なんか失くして
Dear humanity, having lost clear skies,
大抵が最低です
most things are at their worst.
廃材置き場の毎日で
Amidst everyday scrap yards,
「衛星都市にいこう」 あなたは言った
"Let's go to the satellite city," you said.
「1.5リットルの現実逃避計画さ」
"It's a 1.5-liter reality-escape plan."
乱反射 世界が透けて
The scattering world shines through,
サイレンが遠くで鳴った もう対流圏界面
and a siren echoed in the distance, at the tropopause.
週末、ぼくら月の裏側で
On the weekend, on the far side of the moon,
「なんにもないね」 なんて、くだらなくて笑いあうだろう
laughing together over how pointless it is that "there's nothing at all."
それからぼくらはおちて
And then we fall in love,
この旅の果てなんてわかっていたって知らないふりさ
knowing how this journey ends, yet pretending not to know.
今なら
Now,
八月の雪が降った あの日は
The day snow fell in August,
ビードロを覗いたように見えた
it looked as though we peered through a glass toy.
「ねえ涙がなんだか止まないんだ昨日から」
"Hey, somehow my tears haven't stopped since yesterday,"
わずかに崩壊する都市が見えた
a slightly collapsing city could be seen.
それは最後の夏でした
That was our final summer.
週末、ぼくら月の裏側で
On the weekend, on the far side of the moon,
傷付け合うのなんて馬鹿らしくて笑いあうだろう
laughing together over how foolish it is to hurt each other.
それからぼくらはおちて
And then we fall in love,
ふたり気付いていたってもうね、この夢はさめないよ
both of us realizing it, yet this dream won't fade away.
そうさぼくら世界の片隅で
That's right, in a corner of the world,
「無くしてばっか」 なんて心なんて埋まらなくても
Even if hearts filled only with "losses" cannot be healed,
何度もぼくら星を巡るよ！
we will wander the stars over and over!
拾った銀貨使ってジュース買って
Buying juice with found silver coins,
分け合って飲もう 「サイダーがいいな」
sharing it to drink: "I'd like some cider."
不思議な顔すると
When you make a funny face,
なぜかキミが愛しくなる
somehow you become so dear to me.
その素振り、仕草に恋しちゃったみたいなんだ
I seem to have fallen in love with those gestures and behaviors.
これからまた、遠く離れている星に行ってしまうなんて イヤだけどこれだけは言わせてね 「また会えるさ。」
Even though I hate that we'll be going off to distant stars once again, just let me say this: "We'll meet again."
「離れたくない」 いつだってそばにいるよ
"I don't want to be apart." I'll always be by your side.
だってもっと一緒にいたいのか ずっとそっと見てるからね
Because I want to be together more, I'll keep watching over you softly, always.
ふたりで描こう 人生日記
Let's draw our life diary together.
新しい星にも
Even on a new star...
新しい生活にも慣れたつもりでいたけど
I've been trying to get used to it all, but...
なにかもの足りない
Something's still missing.
キミの笑い声だった
It was your smiling voice!
あれからどれくらい カレンダーをめくったのかな
How many days have passed since then, as I flipped through the calendar?
ひとりでは 帰り道 道草もしないから
When I'm all by myself, the way home is so lonely...
怒られない 涙が出るの…
I won't let myself cry!
いつだってそばにいるよ だってもっと一緒にいたいよ
I'll always be right by your side, no matter what!
ずっとそっと見てるからね ふたりで描こう
I'll always, always keep watching over you.
人生日記
Our life diary together!
ラブラブピポー ピッパリピポー
Love love pi-po, pipipari pi-po!
いつだってそばにいるよ だってもっと一緒にいたいよ
I'll always be right by your side, no matter what!
ずっとそっと見てるからね ふたりで描こう
I'll always, always keep watching over you.
人生日記 そうこのまま 時を越えて
Our life diary together, transcending time just as we are!
誰の声も届かない そう ふたりだけの場所へ
To a place where nobody's voice can reach,
ココロをつなぐ人生日記
Connecting our hearts in our life diary!
ふたりで描こう 人生日記
Let's draw our life diary together!
ひとりが辛いから ふたつの手をつないだ
Because being alone is so lonely, we joined our hands together.
ふたりじゃ寂しいから 輪になって手をつないだ
Because being together is lonely, we formed a circle and joined hands.
きっとそれが幾千の 力にもなり どんな夢も断てる気がするんだ
Surely that becomes the strength of thousands, making us feel like we can overcome any dream.
高く飛べ 高く空へ 高く蹴れ 高く声を上げ
Fly high, high into the sky, kick high, raise your voice high!
いつか挫けた その日の向こうまで
Go beyond that day when we were disheartened.
きみの声忘れない 涙も忘れない
I won't forget your voice, nor your tears!
これから始まる 希望という名の未来を その足は歩き出す
Walking forward into a future called hope that begins from now on.
やがて来る過酷も
Even towards the cruel fate to come.
時にはきみがどこにいるのかもわからなくなって
Sometimes I lose sight of where you might be,
そっと誰かがくれた優しい言葉が
But then, someone gently gave me...
きみのものだと教えてくれたんだ
Kind words that taught me they were truly yours.
腕をかき 風を切れ 前を向き 涙が滲むほどに
Stroke with your arms, cut through the breeze, face forward until your eyes are blurred with tears,
真っ直ぐこの空を駆け抜けろ
And run straight through this sky!
きみもひとり 僕もひとり みんなが孤独でいるんだ この輪の中で
Everyone is alone, yet here we are together in this circle.
輪の中で気づかないうちに
Within the circle, before I even realized,
その足は震え出す
those feet begin to tremble.
小さな過酷にも
Even through little hardships,
僕ら皆同じ夢を見てた
we all dreamed the same dream.
過ぎ去る1ページの
Of a passing single page—
ここからは一冊しか持って行けないよ
from here on, we can only take one book.
それでよかったのかい？
Was that really okay?
胸には強さを 気高き強さを
Strength in our hearts, noble strength,
頬には涙を 一滴の涙を
and tears on our cheeks, a single drop.
高く跳べ 高く空へ 高く跳ね 高く声を上げ
Jump high, high to the sky, leap high, raise your voice!
いつか挫けたその日の向こうまで
Beyond that day when we once faltered,
きみの声忘れない 涙も忘れない
I won't forget your voice, nor your tears.
これから始まる希望という名の未来を
Toward the future named hope about to begin,
その足は歩き出す
those feet start to walk.
やがて来る過酷も 乗り越えてくれるよ
I know you'll overcome the hardships yet to come,
信じさせてくれるよ
you make me believe in it.
サマータイムレコード / 作詞・作曲・編曲：じん
[Summer Time Record / Lyrics & Music: Jin]
昨日も今日も晴天で入道雲を見てた
Yesterday and today too, I watched the clouds.
戯れくらいの快晴だ 随分に目を閉じて
Closing my eyes in the playful fair weather.
「それ」はどうも簡単に思い出やしない様で
"That" wasn't something easily remembered,
年を取った現状に浸ってたんだよ
so I was soaking in the reality of aging.
あー
Ah...
大人ぶった作戦で 不思議な合図たてて
With grown-up strategies and strange signals,
「行こうか、今日も戦争だ」 立ち向かって 手を取った
"Let's go, today is a war too," taking hands.
理不尽なんて当然で 独りぼっち置かれて
Unreasonableness was natural, left all alone,
迷子な僕等 鬱に練りそうになってさ
we lost children were sinking into depression.
背中を分けて 滲む太陽 炎天下
Separating backs, under the glaring sun.
君はさ、こう言ったんだ 「孤独だったら、おいでよ」
You said, "If you're lonely, come over."
騒がしさがノックして 生まれた感情さえも
Even the emotions born from bustle
頭に浮かんではしぼんだ 幻なのかな
faded away—was it an illusion?
秘密基地に集まって 「楽しいね」って単純な
Gathering in the secret base, simple times
あの頃を思い出して 話をしようよ
like back then, let's talk about them.
飛行機雲飛んで行って 「眩しいね」って泣いていた
Condensation trails flew, crying "It's dazzling."
君はどんな顔だっけ なぜだろう、思い出せないな
What was your face like? I can't remember.
痛いくらいに現実は 足早に駆け抜けた
Realities painful to the core rushed past.
選んだ今日は平凡で 崩れそうになる日々さ
The chosen today is ordinary and fragile.
昨日の今日も延長戦 大人だって臆病だ
Yesterday and today are extra innings for cowards.
今になってなんとなく 気づけたみたいだよ
Now, somehow, it feels like I've realized.
廻るセカイのイデア 枯れる太陽 炎天下
The spinning world's idea, under scorching sun.
陽炎が揺らいだ 「忘れないで、さあ、進もう」
Heat hazes flickered—"Let's move forward."
忘れないで、さぁ、進もう。
"Don't forget, now, let's move forward."
もどかしさに何度も
No matter how many times in frustration,
明日を夢見ていた
I dreamed of tomorrow.
戻らない、先の或る世界へ
To a world without return, but with a future ahead,
「僕たちで変えよう」
"Let's change it ourselves."
「思い出して、終わったって?」
"Remember? It's all over?"
秘密基地も、冒険も、
Secret bases and adventures,
あの日に迷い込んだ話のことも、
And the story of getting lost on that day too,
独りぼっちが集まった
A gathering of lonely souls,
子供たちの作戦がまた今日も廻り出した
The children's operation started spinning once again today.
「また、何処かで。」
"Somewhere else, again."
「涼しいね」って言い合った
"It's nice and cool," we told each other.
夏空は透明だ
The summer sky is transparent.
泣かない様に、吸い込んで、
Breathing it in so as not to cry,
「さようならしよう」
"Let's say goodbye."
秘密基地に集まって
Gathering at the secret base,
笑い合った夏の日に
On that summer day when we laughed together,
また何処かで思い出して出逢えるかなって
Remembering it somewhere again, wondering if we'll meet...
何度でも描こう
Let's paint it over and over again.
明日も明後日もきっと一人じゃたどり着けない
Tomorrow and the day after, I surely couldn't reach it alone.
涙の数の想いだけ伝えたくて
Wanting to convey just the feelings equal to the number of tears.
あの日始まったキズナ結ぶ戸惑いの日々が
The days of hesitation forming bonds that began that day
気づけば近づく心の距離
If I realize it, the distance between our hearts is closing.
上手く紡げない言葉だけど不器用なりに歩いてきた
Even though my words aren't woven well, I've walked in my own clumsy way.
巡る奇跡
Miracles circling,
いつか枯れる運命でも咲き誇る花でありたい
Even in a fate that eventually withers, I want to be a blooming flower.
いつか焦る想いでも まだ夢見たいから
Even with impatient feelings, I still want to dream.
明日も明後日もきっと一人じゃたどり着けない 涙の数の想いだけ 心にあふれてる
Tomorrow and the day after, I couldn't reach it alone; feelings of the number of tears overflow in my heart.
それでも最後は魔法のように いつか消えてしまうのなら
Even so, if the end is like magic and will someday disappear,
伝え足りない気持ち君に届くように
So that my unexpressed feelings reach you,
そっと今に願う
Softly, I wish upon the present.
振り返れば今生も過去は未来の証明
Looking back, even this lifetime, the past is proof of the future.
胸に重なってって ずっとうまく伝わらない
Overlapping in my chest, it never transmits well.
でもいつだって感じてたよ きっと出会いの意味は僕らが決めるもの
But I always felt it; surely the meaning of our encounter is something we decide.
そうでしょ 明日も明後日も大げさな未来じゃなくても
Right? Tomorrow and the day after, even if it's not an exaggerated future,
涙の数のキズナで これから幸せで
With bonds made from the number of tears, happily from now on...
それでも泣いたり笑ったり 傷つくこともあるでしょう
Even so, there will be times when we cry, laugh, or get hurt.
これまであった奇跡 いつも思い出して
Always remembering the miracles we've had until now.
触れ合うたび近づく奇跡
The miracle of growing closer every time we touch,
巡り会えた君との奇跡
the miracle of meeting you—
すべてはここから始まる
it all begins right here.
心の弱さを見せること そんな悪いことじゃない
Showing the weakness in my heart isn't such a bad thing.
6年分の笑顔をありがとう
Thank you for six years' worth of smiles.
これまで紡がれた奇跡 思いあふれ出して現代
The miracles spun together until now overflow into the present—
揺るぎないもの一つ言葉じゃ伝えられない
one unshakeable thing that words alone cannot convey.
それでもさようならは絆の いつか辿り着く
Even so, farewells are ties we will someday reach...
着地点で登る東雲より
at the destination, brighter than the dawn climbing up,
夜に染まるようにだから永久を願う
dyeing into the night, so I wish for eternity.
皆さんどうもこんあくあー！
Hello everyone, Kon-Aqua!
ホロライブ所属湊あくあです！
I'm Minato Aqua from Hololive!
ということで もういっこ声変わってる？
So, wait, has my voice changed again?
ここからは生パフォーマンスでお送りします！
From here on, we'll bring you a live performance!
えードキュメンタリーやごうとね、対談してみたりとか
Um, doing a documentary, or having a dialogue,
すごい声の可愛いナレーションがあったりとか、みんなと歌を歌ったりとか色々あったんですけども！
having cute voice narration, singing songs with everyone, and various other things, but...
どうでしたか？いかがでしたか？
how was it? How did you like it?
ということで、今日は卒業ライブということで、私の最後のライブ
So, today is my graduation live, my final live,
最後まで見てってね、お願います！
please watch all the way to the end, I ask of you!
えー、ハッシュタグ「#湊あくあ卒業ライブ」で、ぜひたくさんツイートしてください！
Um, please tweet a lot using the hashtag "#MinatoAquaGraduationLive"!
なんか、日本トレンド1位、世界トレンド1位って書いてあるわ、台本に。台本とか言わないの！
It says "Japan Trend #1, World Trend #1" in the script. Hey, I shouldn't say "script"!
はい、ということでね、たくさんありがとうございます！
Yes, so thank you all so much!
えー、ということで、湊あくあは、今日で伝説になる！銀河一伝説のアイドル湊あくあを目にしっかり焼き付けてね！絶対だよ！
Um, so, Minato Aqua becomes a legend today! Make sure to burn me, the galaxy's most legendary idol Minato Aqua, firmly into your eyes! Absolutely, okay?
ということで次の曲へ行く前に、ちょっとね、あの喉パッサパサ、緊張してパッサパサなんで、ちょっとお水飲みます。ちょっと待って。
So before moving on to the next song, um, my throat is parched, I'm so nervous my throat is dry, so I'll drink some water. Just a second.
やばい、緊張すごいんだけど。あ、お水ってこんなに美味しいんだね。よし。
Oh no, I'm so nervous. Ah, water is so delicious. Okay.
お待たせしました！えー、ハンドマイクからヘッドセットに変えました！かわいいでしょ？
Thanks for waiting! Um, I changed from a hand mic to a headset! Cute, right?
ということで、それでは次の曲聞いてください。あくたんのこと好きすぎ☆ソング！
And with that, please listen to the next song. "Akutan's Super-Duper Love Song!"
あくたんのこと好きすぎ☆ソング
Akutan's Super-Duper Love Song
ドジっ子メイドはてててと舞い踊り
A clumsy maid dances around,
洗濯ほら汗だくとお料理焦がしたらてへぺろの許してご主人
doing laundry—look, all sweaty! If I burn the cooking, give me a "tehepero" and forgive me, Master!
ゲームばかりして怒ってるプリティーネコフェイスでごまかすにゃ
Getting all worked up playing games, covering it up with a pretty cat face, nya!
お昼寝はメイドの特権ご機嫌な夢見てすーやよ
Napping is a maid's privilege, having a cheerful dream, suu-ya!
エプロンカチューシャはハンドメイドの
Apron and headband are handmade!
メイド服を着たらだんだんおんなの子だけど
Idol me is a maid, you know? Ahaha!
ご主人様に見つかってる!
My husband is looking!
どめ、とめ!
Tometome!
メイド服を着たらだんだんおんなの子だけど
Once I put on my maid uniform,
だんだんおんなの子だけど
I start acting a bit more like a girl.
ご主人様との思い出作りますか?
Shall we make memories with my husband?
ずっと仲良くしてねっ!
Let's stay on good terms forever, okay?
はるか未来でしわくちゃになったって
Far away in the future,
しわくちゃになったって
even if we get wrinkly and old,
思い出作ってくんだよね、この!
we'll still be making memories together, right?
じゅっおむらいす!
Omuraisu!
ちゃんと食べて!
Let's eat it up!
みなとあくあフルコース巡り行くよ!
Minato Aqua's full-course memory trip!
きらきらと輝こうか
Sparkling and shining bright,
間違えちゃっても大丈夫
it's okay even if we make mistakes.
できないことできるよに
We can do the things we couldn't before,
なれるよ先は長いから
because the path ahead is long.
疲れちゃったら一休みして
If you get tired, let's take a little break,
またやりたいことしたいように
then start wanting to do things all over again!
しなくちゃあたしじゃないでしょ?
It's not like we have no choice, right?
忘れないよこの思いは
Never forget these feelings.
重ねてもっと届くように
If we stack them up, they'll reach even further,
変えられるんだ変えていくんだ
because we can change them, we'll keep going!
きらきらしたいから、はい、ちーず!
I want to sparkle, so say hi-cheese!
うつむいて泣いてみたって全然可愛くない
Even if you look down and cry, it's not cute at all.
君だって同じ波折の人生です
You're just the same as me,
波折の人生です
a life of rough waves.
そんな優しくしないで私の気があるの、この!
Why are you being so nice?
もうどんな時間? どんな予感? カタストロフィ?
What's this timing? What's this happening?
あ、16歳少女 胃酸過多 メンタル崩壊
Ah, 16-year-old stomach upset! Mental breakdown!
あなたのことをもっともっと知りたい!
I want to know more, more about you!
Starting up! ヨーコソ! Sweet Carnival!
Starting up! Yo-koso! Sweet Carnival!
あなたの大好きがいっぱい溢れた街
Overflowing with the town's favorite things,
鳴らそう胸のパレード
let's ring out our smiles with a proud chest!
色彩はもっと奇跡が飛び出してくることはホラライブ!
The colors are miracles, and the things leaping out are hurray!
一緒に楽しもう現代 あなたの未来やっと掴んだ世界を繋げることでアクロバット
Let's connect worlds with your dream!
アクロバット!
Acrobat!
エイムに愛されしガールなんてね分からないけどさ
A girl loved by AIM, I don't really understand,
なんだってできる気するわ
but I feel like I can do anything!
エイムの世界ならならば
If this is the world of AIM, then...
エイムに愛されしガールなんてね分からないけどさ
A girl loved by AIM, I don't really understand,
自分らしくいられないなら駄目でしょ
but if I can't even stay true to myself,
それなら準備はOK
If that's the case, my preparation is ready,
踏み込もうって全然!
I'm diving headfirst into it all!
プリンセス・キャリー よろしかおっしゃーすです
Princess Carry, nice to meet you!
てきぱき出すピアラをわざと見せつけて
Showing off a bit of swagger, let's make a scene!
恋の魔法ちゃお愛嬌で 人魚が化けて全て泡になっていく
If we fall in love, everything will turn into bubbles!
ねえ キャリー お姫様のはあなたがいつか触れた幸せで
Hey Carry, if the happiness you once touched
満たされたらいいのにな
could be fulfilled, that would be wonderful!
よそ見しない覚悟ができたならOK
If you have the resolve not to hesitate,
One, two, three ここからは
One, two, three, from here on out,
投げ捨ててもいいけど
even if you throw it all away, it's fine!
これぐらいのはわがままは おんなの子してぬってことじゃ
But this is just how an ordinary girl acts, right?
One by one 言葉で教えてほしい
One by one, I want you to teach me with words!
パブゲゲーム見た!
Pubg game, let's see!
もうすり抜かないでずっとずっと何処かできないなくしちゃいそう、どうせ？どこでも？
If you can't slip away, let's just make it happen!
攻略しない!
Let's not strategize!
いつかの憧れた 華やかな世界
In a world I once longed for, so glamorous and bright,
強がってみせてても “怖いよ 怖いよ”
even if I try to act tough, "I'm scared, I'm scared."
メリーゴーランドの中で ひとりぼっちみたい
Inside the merry-go-round, I feel all alone,
掠れそうな声で 【気付いて 気付いて】
with a voice that's about to fade, [Notice me, notice me].
群集の中で キミの声が聴こえる
In the crowd, I can hear your voice,
聞き間違えじゃない 【呼んでよ 呼んでよ】
it's not a misunderstanding, [Call me, call me].
聴こえたその声に 心が熱くなる
That voice I heard, makes my heart burn,
ダメダメでもいいかな 隣にいたいよ
even if it's no good, I just want to be by your side.
だからきっと たぶん絶対
Because, because, because, because it's you,
これはキミのせい そう覚えていてね
so surely, probably definitely, this is all your fault.
(秘密にしているの)キミの「大好き」の証
(I'm keeping it a secret,) Your proof of "I love you."
(教えてよ)魔法みたいに輝いて
(Tell me,) Shine like magic,
(聞かせてよ)おとぎ話ようなお話
(Tell me a story,) A fairy tale-like story.
(見せてみて)私ひとりじゃ叶えない
(Show me,) I can't make it come true alone.
(Oh Ah Oh Ah Oh)
(Oh, ah-oh, ah-oh,)
キミが隣にただいるだけで
Just having you by my side, just being next to you,
プリンセスになれるの
makes me a princess.
運命で出会って 一緒にみた世界
Destined to meet, the world we saw together,
改まって照れるけど ありがとう 大好きだよ
I feel shy when I say it, thank you, I love you.
毎日の中で キミの声が聴こえる
In my everyday life, I can hear your voice,
世界中で1番私が幸せだよ
in the whole world, I'm the happiest.
ティアラも ドレスだって ガラスの靴なんかも
The tiara, the dress, and the glass slippers too.
全部いらないわ キミが全て
All I don't need, you are everything.
キミと歩いたキセキ
The miracle of walking with you,
絶対だよって約束 覚えている?
do you remember the promise that it's absolute?
私ひとりじゃ キミがいないとちぐはぐで
If I'm alone by myself, without you there with me,
輝かないわ
I can't shine.
嘘みたいな程 キミを大好きな私
It feels like a lie, how much I love you,
(I LOVE YOU)ぱれっとみたいに彩って
(I love you.) Coloring like a palette,
(I LOVE YOU SO MUCH)ホントだけ上の物語
(I love you so much.) A story that's truly ours.
(I LOVE YOU)未来はどうなるのかな
(I love you.) I wonder what the future will be like.
(Oh Ah Oh Ah Oh)闇もない
(Oh, ah-oh, ah-oh.) There's no darkness,
不安も消える
the anxiety disappears.
そうやって描いた今日を乗り越して
So that's how we drew today,
明日はもっとキミのそばへ 前へ そう前へ
tomorrow is even closer to your side.
少しずつ進んでく
Stepping forward little by little,
一歩十歩百歩踏み出して 揺らめいてるキミが あおく滲む
stepping with 1, 10, 100, 1000 steps, unsteady Aqua.
あおく滲む 綺麗に
Aqua, Aqua, cleanly.
会いに行こう 会いに行こう 今すぐ
Let's go meet, let's go meet right now.
満ちていく キミに届けて
Reaching you, uni-birth,
超える夜はあたたかな愛を
nights that cross over have a warm love.
嫌われる前に嫌ってきたくせに
Before being hated, I came to hate you,
さみしくないみたい と思おうの
honestly, I want to say "Nice to meet you."
涙も ぜんぶ いつか
Tears, dreams, someday
花開くように春も巡る
they will bloom like flowers, spring is turning around.
憧れた姿と違っているはずが
It should be different from the person I longed to be,
たぶんらしくいたいと思うの
honestly, I want to say "Nice to meet you."
ユニバース 生まれ変わっても
Uni-birth, even if I am reborn,
私がいいと思わないよ だってさ
I wouldn't think anyone else is better, so.
憧れる 今が未来の私
Yearning for now, my future self,
もっとらしくの生ききりをしてる
living out my own unique way.
かっこいいだろ? かっこよく見えるんじゃないか
Doesn't it look wonderfully cool?
この告白を終わらないで
Let's not end this confession!
負けたくない悔し涙が
Tears of regret that I didn't want to shed,
あふれたドレスすらも
overflowed even the superhero cape.
無駄じゃない私らしさを 作っていこう
Let's create this undeniable authenticity.
だから 大丈夫 大丈夫 心配ないよ 大丈夫 大丈夫
Tomorrow, alright, alright, don't worry, alright, alright.
全力で走り続けたんだ キミならできるさ
I kept running with all my might, because it's you, I can do it!
喜びも 悲しみも 分かち合える
Joy also, sadness also, sharing them,
人がいる 初めて気づいたんだ 一人じゃないんだって
I've realized for the first time, it's not just me!
叶えたい 夢はきっと この場所で
That dream I want to fulfill, surely in this place,
あすあいに 二人輝く
Aqua and I will shine forever!
A!Q!U!A! いくよ Let's go! Fight, win!
A-Q-U-A, here we go, Let's go! Fight, win!
海想列車 も怖くない
The marginal train isn't scary either.
夢中で駆け抜けた日々は 夢じゃないから
Days dashed through in a daze aren't a dream.
世界なんて相変わらず まだわからないけど
I still don't know the right answer, but
目の前に広がる この景色を見でいたい
seeing this scenery spread out before my eyes,
この景色を見でいたい 君と一緒に
I want to see this scenery together with you.
見たい見たい
I want to watch...
やり切った！
I did it!
長かった！
It was so long!
ちょっと喉パサパサなので、お水飲みます。
My throat's a bit dry, so I'm going to drink some water.
やばい、やばいパサパサだ...
Oh no, oh no, it's so dry...
お水が美味しすぎる。
This water is too delicious.
ちょっと待って。
Hold on a second.
とんでもないわ、あーちょっと疲れた。
This is unbelievable... Ah, I'm a bit tired.
あれ？ なんかこれ... 新しいマイク？
Huh? What is this? A new microphone?
ということで、ありがとうございました！1曲目メドレーでした！私の歌とダンスいかがだったでしょうか？
So, thank you very much! That was our first song medley!
How did you like my singing and dancing?
ちょっと待って、やばい。オリジナルハンドマイクになりました！なーまー！
Wait a second, oh no.
It became an original hand mic! Na-ma-!
ちょっとめっちゃさ、ちょっと息やばくて、とんでもないことになってる。
I'm huffing and puffing so much right now,
my breathing is in terrible shape.
あ、コメントね、すごいね、早すぎてあのね読めません！はい。あの読めないです。もうとんでもない加速の漁師でありがとうございますみんな！
Ah, the comments are moving so fast
I can't read them! Yeah. I can't read them.
Thank you everyone for the incredible acceleration!
疲れた、ちょっと待って。
I'm exhausted, hold on.
あー、呼吸を整えて、ちょっとまだ緊張も覚めやらぬところではありますが
Ah, catching my breath... The tension
hasn't quite worn off yet, though.
えー、ま、最後だからね、えー全部、おり曲歌いたいなって思ってたので、全部歌うにはもう24時間必要だということで、激長のメドレーにさせていただきました！ありがとうございますみんな！
Um, since it's the final time, I wanted to sing
all the original songs, but that would take 24 hours,
so I made it an ultra-long medley! Thank you everyone!
6年間ね、こんなにたくさんオリジナル曲を作ったんだなと、本当にたくさんの歌を歌えて幸せでした！ありがとうございます！えー携わってくださった皆さん、聴いてくれたみんな、本当にどうもありがと！
For 6 years, to think I created so many original songs...
I was truly happy to sing so many songs! Thank you!
To everyone involved and everyone who listened, thank you!
えー、次の曲はですね、このライブの直前に動画が上がった曲です。
Um, the next song is a song whose video
was uploaded right before this live.
えー、ちょっと緊張してきた。
Um, I'm starting to get nervous.
ちょっとお水も、ちょっと待って。やばい、ちょっと待って。お水飲みすぎ？
Let me drink some water too... wait a second.
Oh no, hold on. Did I drink too much water?
あのね、人は緊張するとね、水、喉が渇くから水を飲みたくなるらしいですよ。噂によると。
You know, when people get nervous, their throat gets dry
so they want to drink water, apparently. According to rumors.
ということで、えー、よっし。えーみんなへ、6年間の感謝を込めて歌います。
So, um, alright. Um, to everyone,
I will sing with gratitude for the past 6 years.
次の曲、聞いてください。今日、初めて歌います。「きみいろプリンセス」
Please listen to the next song.
Today, I'm singing it for the first time. "Kimiiro Princess".
いつかの憧れた 華やかな世界
In a world I once longed for,
so glamorous and bright,
強がってみせても “怖いよ 怖いよ”
Even if I try to act tough,
"I'm scared, I'm scared."
メリーゴーランドの中で ひとりぼっちみたい
Inside the merry-go-round,
I feel all alone,
擦れそうな声で 【気付いて 気付いて】
With a voice that's about to fade,
[Notice me, notice me.]
群集の中で キミの声が聞こえる 聞き間違いじゃない 【呼んでよ 呼んでよ】
In the crowd, I can hear your voice,
It's not a misunderstanding, [Call me, call me.]
聞こえたその声に 心が熱くなる
That voice I heard,
makes my heart burn,
ダメダメでもいいかな 隣にいたいよ
Even if it's no good,
I just want to be by your side.
だってだってだって だってキミだから だからきっと
Because, because, because,
because it's you, So surely,
たぶん絶対 これはきミのせい そう覚えておいて
Probably definitely,
This is all your fault, So remember that.
(秘密にしてるの)
(I'm keeping it a secret,)
キミの「大好き」の証 (教えてよ)
your proof of "I love you." (Tell me,)
魔法みたいに輝いて (聞かせてよ)
shine like magic, (Tell me a story,)
おとぎのようなお話 (見せてみて)
a fairy tale-like story, (Show me,)
私ひとりじゃ叶えない (Oh Ah Oh Ah Oh)
I can't make it come true alone, (Oh Ah Oh Ah Oh)
キミが隣にただいるだけで
Just having you right by my side
プリンセスになれるの
is enough to make me a princess.
運命で出会って 一緒にみた世界
Meeting by fate, the world we saw together
改まって照れるけど ありがとう 大好きだよ
I'm a bit shy to say, but thank you, I love you!
毎日の中で キミの声が聞こえる
Amidst everyday life, I can hear your voice.
世界中で1番 私が幸せだよ
I am the happiest person in the entire world.
ティアラも ドレスだって
Tiara, dress,
ガラスの靴なんかも 全部いらないわ
even glass slippers—I don't need any of it.
キミが全て
You are my everything!
キミと歩いたキセキ
The miracle of walking with you—
絶対だよって約束 覚えてる？
do you remember our promise that it's forever?
私ひとりじゃ キミがいないくちゃ
By myself, without you here,
輝けないわ
I wouldn't be able to shine.
嘘みたいなほど キミを大好きな私 (I LOVE YOU)
Loving you so much it feels like a lie (I LOVE YOU)
ぱれっとみたいに彩って (I LOVE YOU SO MUCH)
Coloring it like a palette (I LOVE YOU SO MUCH)
ホントだけの物語 (I LOVE YOU)
A story made only of truth (I LOVE YOU)
未来はどうなるのかな (Oh Ah Oh Ah Oh)
What will the future hold? (Oh Ah Oh Ah Oh)
暗闇もない不安も消える ずっと進んでいこう
Darkness and anxiety disappear, let's keep moving forward!
これからも 私を見てて
Keep watching over me from now on too.
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
キミイロプリンセスでした！
That was "#KimiIroPrincess"!
もうやばい緊張で… やばい、なんか足くなっちゃいそう…
I was so nervous... Oh gosh, my legs are shaking so much...
えー、ということでこの曲は、え、キミイロパレットのアンサーソングとして、え、ジャッキーさんと一緒に作りました。
Um, so, this song was created as an answer song to "#KimiIroPalette" together with Jacky-P.
私もちっょとだけ作詞をさせていただきました。いっぱい聴いてください。
I also wrote a little bit of the lyrics myself. Please listen to it a lot!
お願いします！
I'm begging you!
え、もうここまで来ちゃったのか。やばい、ちょっと待って、水の方…
Wow, we've already come this far. Oh no, wait, let me get some water...
あああ、ここまで来ちゃったの…
Ahhh, we've really made it this far...
うわ、やばい、どうしよう… もう、ここまで歌っちゃったんだ…
Whoa, oh no, what do I do... I've already sung this far...
いや、マジか… ちょっとなんかやっと実感が湧いてきた。やばい、やばいしか言ってないな。
Man, seriously... It's finally starting to sink in. Oh gosh, all I'm saying is "oh gosh."
泣きそうなんだけど…
I feel like crying...
待って、え、本当にちょっとさ、あの次の曲ボロボロでも許してくれますか？
Wait, um, seriously, if the next song is a complete mess, will you forgive me?
まあ、ちょっとお話をね、させていただきたいと思うんですけれど、いいですか？
Well, I'd like to talk to you all for a bit, is that okay?
ええと、しゃべりますね。泣いても笑っても、これで卒業ということで…
Um, I'll talk now. Whether I cry or smile, with this, graduation is...
アイドルにとって「好き」っていうのは、みんなに忘れられることだと、私は思ってます。
For an idol, I believe that being "loved" means eventually being forgotten by everyone.
これからも、私は私でいるよ。
From now on too, I will stay being myself.
卒業しても、まだまだ生きていくんだから。だからみんなも、私のこと忘れないでね。
Even after graduating, I'm still going to keep living on. So everyone, please don't forget about me!
本当に…忘れないでね…
Really... please don't forget me...
考えるタイプなんですけど、
I tend to overthink things, but...
私はホロライブに入ったときから 最後は輝いて終わりたいって思ってました 漠然とね
Ever since I joined Hololive, I always wanted my ending to shine bright. Vaguely, you know.
そう思うと ある意味この卒業も 私のひとつの夢だったんだなと 思います
Thinking about it that way, in a sense, this graduation was one of my dreams too, I think.
物心ついたときから ずっとアイドルになりたかった
Ever since I was old enough to know better, I've always wanted to be an idol.
私 幼稚園のときの夢が アイドルだったんですよ
My dream back in kindergarten was to be an idol!
はずい！本当に なんか ちょっと本当は あの ちょっとすかしてケーキ屋さんとかおもちゃ屋さんとか あの 親に言ったりはしたんですけど
So embarrassing! Really... I mean, actually, I told my parents I wanted to be a cake shop or toy store owner to play it cool, but...
キラキラ輝くアイドルになりたいなって 歌って踊れるアイドルになりたいなって みんなに愛されるアイドルになりたいなって 思ってました
I wanted to be a sparkling idol, one who sings and dances, and is loved by everyone. That's what I dreamed of.
すごくない？ 夢をかなえたんだよ みんなのおかげで
Isn't that amazing? I made my dream come true, thanks to everyone.
自分の部屋と 1台のパソコン 暗い部屋で ただパソコンに向かって 喋っていただけの私が 私の環境が みんなのおかげで どんどん変わっていって
My own room and a single PC. Just a girl sitting in a dark room talking to her computer. My environment changed so much thanks to all of you,
本当にこんなことって あるんだね
that it really makes you feel like miracles like this actually happen.
この奇跡が 積み重ねてきた 想いが きっと私のこれからを 支えてくれると思う
I'm sure all these accumulated miracles and feelings will support me in whatever comes next.
そういうふうに 今思えてることを 誇りに思います
I'm proud that I can feel this way right now.
だから改めて みんな 本当にありがとう！
So once again, thank you all so very much!
これさ なんかさお辞儀したさ お辞儀した 秒数だけみたいなのあったりするかな もっといっぱいおじぎしといたほうがいいかな 本当にみんなありがとう
You know, I wonder if there's a record for how many seconds I bowed. Maybe I should have bowed more. Thank you all so much!
それでは ちょっと名残惜しいんですけども 私たちは今日伝説になりますから ね
Well then, as reluctant as I am... today we become legends, right?
歌えるかな
I wonder if I can sing.
次は最後の曲です
Next is our final song.
それでは 最後の曲 聞いてください あくあ色ぱれっと
So please listen to the final song: "Aqua Iro Palette".
何をしても不器用で
I'm so clumsy in everything that I do,
何かとミスしてばっか
things go wrong cause I make mistakes a lot.
ダメダメな私だって
Even a useless me like this
できる事があるの
has something she can do!
凹んで悲しくたって
When you're feeling blue and sad,
笑顔にしてあげるんだ
I'll make you smile.
ここにいるから 早く
I'm right here, so hurry up
私を見つけてね
and find me!
これで本当の本当に愛されず！
With this, I'm truly, truly loved!
まずなんだこれ でこで これに乗りまーす！
Wait, what is this? I'm riding on this!
love you love you...
いつでも隣にいるし、
I'll always be by your side,
いつでも一緒に笑える
and we can always laugh together.
私をたくさん知って
Get to know me better
たくさん好きって言って
and tell me you love me lots!
ワガママで朝も苦手
Not a morning person and so selfish,
ドジだしダメダメだけど
I'm all thumbs and good for nothing,
それでも私の事を
but still, please keep your eyes
見ててね 描く夢の未来へ…
on me as we head toward the future of our dreams...
描く夢の未来へ続く
The way to the future that I'm dreaming of,
道をキミと歩けますように
I wish I could walk this path with you.
ねぇもっと好きになってもらいたいの!
Hey, please love me even more!
頭の中はキミばっかだってゆうか
My head is full of you!
そっぽ向かないで、 ahもう！
Don't look away, oh please,
ヤキモチしちゃうわ ah
I'm getting so jealous, ah.
ずっとずっと好きがいいの
I want you to love me more and more,
心の中もトキメキちゃうくらいに
My heart is beating so fast,
こっち向いててよね、ダーリン?
Look at me, darling?
あぁもう離さないから、絶対に!
I'll never let you go, so absolutely!
love you love you...
キミがいるから私いつでも頑張れるんだ
I can do my best because you're here.
落ち込んで悲しくたってキミがいるから…
Even when I'm feeling down and sad...
今日が本当に最後の日にになりました!
Today truly became my final day!
キミがいるから歩いてこれた
I was able to walk because you were here.
キミがいないとくしゃ前も見えない
Without you, I couldn't even see ahead.
いやなこととかつらいこととかあったって
Through hard times and painful days,
キミの力でここまで笑ってこれたんだ
I could smile because of your strength.
こんなもっと私がぐっと引っ張って連れて行くんだ
Now it's my turn to pull you along and lead the way!
キミがいるから私がいるの
You are here, so I am here too.
こんな私を愛してくれる?
Will you love someone like me?
ねぇもっと、ねぇもっと、まだもっと受け止めてよね!
Hey more, hey more, please accept me more!
さぁ声を上げて!
Now, let your voice ring out!
ねぇもっと、ねぇもっと好きになってもらいたいの
Hey more, hey more, I want you to love me!
いつでもそう私みたいにそっぽなんて向かせないわ
I can't just act indifferent like I always do,
ねぇほら夢中にしちゃうわ ah
Hey, I'll make you completely obsessed, ah!
ずっずっと好きがいいの
I want you to love me forever and ever,
心も体も蕩まっちゃうくらいに
To the point where my heart and soul race,
こっち向いててよねダーリン?
Look this way, won't you, darling?
あぁもう離さないから、絶対に絶対に絶対よ
I'm never letting go, absolutely, absolutely!
約束だよ!
It's a promise!
love you love you...
愛しちゃうもっと ありがとう!
I love you even more. Thank you!